<?xml version="1.0"?>
<hooks>
	<hook name="save_creature">
		<arg name="this" type="Creature" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever a Creature is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="creature_heartbeat">
		<arg name="this" type="Creature" />
		<doc>Called once per heartbeat for every Creature.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_entity">
		<arg name="this" type="Entity" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever any Entity is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_portal">
		<arg name="this" type="Portal" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever a Portal is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="ready">
		<doc>This hook is called once when the engine first initialized and the game is ready to begin.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="change_hour">
		<doc>Called every time the in-game hour increments.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_npc">
		<arg name="this" type="Npc" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever an Npc is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="npc_death">
		<arg name="this" type="Npc" />
		<arg name="killer" type="Creature" />
		<doc>This hook is called whenever any Npc dies.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="npc_heartbeat">
		<arg name="this" type="Npc" />
		<doc>Called once per heartbeat for every Npc.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_object_blueprint">
		<arg name="this" type="ObjectBlueprint" />
		<arg name="swriter" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever an ObjectBlueprint is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_object">
		<arg name="this" type="Object" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever an Object is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="object_heartbeat">
		<arg name="this" type="Object" />
		<doc>Called once per heartbeat for every Object.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_player">
		<arg name="this" type="Player" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever a Player is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="player_start">
		<arg name="this" type="Player" />
		<doc>Invoked when a player first logins in.  A primary use of this hook is to set a starting Room for the player.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="create_creature">
		<arg name="this" type="Player" />
		<doc>Invoked when a user attempts to create a new creature.  The hook should begin a creature creation process.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="player_death">
		<arg name="this" type="Player" />
		<arg name="killer" type="Creature" />
		<doc>Invoked whenever a Player dies.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="player_heartbeat">
		<arg name="this" type="Player" />
		<doc>Called once per heartbeat for every Player.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_room">
		<arg name="this" type="Room" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever a Room is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="room_heartbeat">
		<arg name="this" type="Room" />
		<doc>Called once per heartbeat for every Room.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="show_room">
		<arg name="this" type="Room" />
		<arg name="viewer" type="Creature" />
		<doc>Invoked whenever a room description is displayed to a creature.  This hook is called just after the description display, and may be used to display additional information about a room.</doc>
	</hook>
	<hook name="save_zone">
		<arg name="this" type="Zone" />
		<arg name="writer" type="ScriptRestrictedWriter" />
		<doc>Called whenever a Zone is saved to disk.  Additional properties may be saved to the writer.</doc>
	</hook>
</hooks>
